Guide to the Howard of Escrick Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Howard of Escrick papers
1640-1641
OSB MSS 61
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.4
(1 box)
The papers contain correspondence and documents pertaining to Charles I's expedition to Scotland in 1640 and 1641, including transcripts of letters from John Pym, John Hampden, and the Committees of Parliamentary Instructions and Ordinances.
Howard of Escrick, Edward Howard, Baron, -1675
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
These papers represent an important collection of source materials surrounding Charles I's expedition to Scotland in 1640 and 1641. Edward Howard, though he originally agreed with the King's decision, was also one of the twelve dissenting peers who signed a petition on 28 August 1640 outlining the popular grievances and dangers attendant on the expedition.
The Howard of Escrick Papers are organized into three chronologically arranged series. Series I, Committee Correspondence includes transcripts of relevant letters from Pym, Hampden, Fiennes, Lord Howard, and the Committees of Parliamentary instructions and ordinances, and letters to Lord Mandeville, Vane, Pym, the Speaker, the Earl of Essex, Hollis, Lord Holland, and others, all concerning the expedition and the reaction among Howard's contemporaries.
Items in Series II, Documents section include a "Sedule contayning the particular sums of the Scotch losses & charges 7 Jan. 1640 (1)," the "Scotch com[missione]rs charge against the Earle of Strafford Dec. 16 1640" and "Instruccons of the Lordes and comons in Parliam[en]t to the Committees of both houses now attending his Royal Ma[jes]t[y] in Scotland." Included in Series III, Letters Cataloged Separately are an autograph letter from Thomas Barrington to Lord Howard, assuring Howard of the country's support of Parliament, and two ALSs from Edward Littleton on the correspondence of a committee appointed by the House of Lords.
Great Britain -- History -- Charles I, 1625-1649; Scotland -- History -- Charles I, 1625-1649; Charles, King of England, I, 1600-1649; Armyne, William, Sir, 1593-1651; Barrington, Thomas, Sir; Bedford, William Russell, Duke of, 1613-1700; Blair, Adam, Sir; Browne, John, 1580-1659; Carnaby, William, Sir; Essex, Robert Devereux, Earl of, 1591-1646; Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 1608-1669; Grandison, William Villiers, Viscount, 1614-1643; Hamilton, James Hamilton, Duke of, 1606-1649; Hampden, John, 1594-1643; Holland, Henry Rich, Earl of, 1590-1649; Holles, Denzil Holles, Baron, 1599-1680; Howard of Escrick, Edward Howard, Baron, -1675; Lauderdale, John Maitland, Duke of, 1616-1682; Littleton, Edward Littleton, Lord, 1589-1645; Loudon, John Campbell, Earl of, 1598-1663; Manchester, Henry Montagu, Earl of, 1563?-1642; Montrose, James Graham, Marquis of, 1612-1650; Pym, John, 1584-1643; Stapleton, Philip, Sir, 1603-1647; Traquair, John Stewart, Earl of, -1659
- Committee Correspondence, 1641 Aug 22; Series I
  - Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to the Speaker Wm. Lenthall, Stilton, 1641 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1 p., 31 x 20 cm
    Scots have disbanded part of their
    army; some mutiny in Lord Carre's
    regiment. Also written to Earl of
    Essex by Lord Howard.
  - Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to John Pym; Stilton, 1641 Aug 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Second letter of this day to Pym
    relays news that Earl of Traquair
    was beheaded in effigy and that
    Earl of Montrose was removed to a
    stricter prison.
  - Fiennes to the Speaker Lenthall, 8 pm, York, 1641 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    2 p., 30 x 20 cm.
    Concerning payment and disbanding
    of troops; need for money; shipment
    of ordnance from Berwick to London.
    Also written to Earl of Essex with
    slight alteration.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Denzil Holles; York, 1641 Aug 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    2 p., 31 x 20 cm
    Requests L 36,000 to disband the
    cavalry, more to disband foot
    soldiers, monies to be collected
    from nine counties in proportion to
    subsidy; Scots disbanded army
    despite Earl of Argyll's opposition
    in Parliament.
  - Lord Howard to Earl of Essex; Darlington, 1641 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1 p., 30 x 21 cm
    Refers problem of gaining commission
    by King's great seal back to
    Parliament; apologizes for any
    discrepancy between his letter and
    a Mr. Nicolls'.
    Also written by Committee to the
    Speaker.
  - All the Committee to the Earl of Holland; Edinburgh, 1641 Aug 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1 p., 31 x 21 cm
    Profuse thanks for a favor; reports
    having met Lord Maitland on the road
    with orders from Parliament for
    Earl of Holland to disband his
    English Army.
  - Lord Howard to Earl of Essex; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    2 p., 31 x 21 cm
    Reports Lord Maitland is on way with
    directions for disbanding Army. Scots
    have ratified the treaty and will do
    so under Great Seal to satisfy
    Parliament of England. Scots still
    have 5000 foot and 500 horse.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Worries over lack of correspondence
    from London, of directions for their
    mission, and of Parliamentary recess.
    Without commission under Great Seal
    can only act as conduit to Parliament
    of England.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Speaker Lenthall; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    On behalf of Sir Michael Ernely,
    officer in garrison at Berwick,
    requests one month's pay for the
    troops (L 3000), and presents John
    Conyer's petition for employment.
  - All the Committee to the Earl of Essex; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    3 p., 30 x 21 cm
    Scots refuse to disband until English
    do; if made to wait, many want
    recompense; previous account of E. of
    Traquair proves false.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    2 p., 30 x 20 cm
    Requests more specific information on
    money to pay off army and garrison to
    satisfy Scots. Urges appropriation of
    the whole sum.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Speaker Leuthall; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1 p., 30 x 20
    King received letter from Spanish
    ambassador re: 4000 soldiers.
    Charles I approved their release from
    army in Ireland in accord with
    Parliament.
  - All the Committee to Earl of Holland; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    From Lord Grandison heard that
    although cavalry is disbanded and
    foot soldiers will be by the 18th,
    money for the garrisons not certain
    Edinburgh promises to pay
    Scots to adhere to treaty when
    appropriate.
  - Lord Howard to Lord Keeper Littleton; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Reports having told Charles I of
    Spanish request for 4,000 men; seeks
    money for garrisons of Berwick and
    Carlisle; Scots will not disband
    their armies until two garrisons
    are discharged. This letter also
    written to Pym by the Committee.
  - All the Committee to Earl of Holland; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Acknowledges Parliament's command to
    disband the army and the artillery
    Scots will likewise disband and
    withdraw regiments facing the
    garrisons of Berwick and Carlisle.
    Hopes for perfect peace.
  - All the Committee to Mr. Treasurer Vane; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Yesterday King delivered to Parliament
    list of councillors minus bishops,
    papists, and prisoners, but including
    Lords Lindsay, Loudon, Dunfermline.
  - Lord Howard, Stapelton, and Hampden to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Orders for disbanding relayed
    ratification of officers and
    councillors; King may leave Oct. 4
    authors want to leave before the
    weather turns bad.
  - All the Committee to Mr. Maxwell; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Thanks for his friend's generous
    accommodations.
  - Lord Howard to Lord Keeper Littleton; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 24 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Reports meeting with Committee of
    the Army over discharge of garrisons
    Scots regiment at Aberdeen to be
    disbanded presently, others when
    English garrisons are. Also sent to
    Mr. Pym from the rest of the
    Committee.
  - All the Committee to unidentified Commissioner of the Treasury; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 25 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    2p., 31 x 20 cm
    L 8,000 for Berwick is insufficient,
    ships needed for transport of
    munitions; Lord Mourtons's removal
    from list of Councillors delays King's
    return, which Committee wishes to
    hasten.
  - Lord Howard to Lord Keeper Littleton; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1 p., 29 x 20 cm
    King's departure likely to be delayed
    one month; wishes to leave to return
    to England sooner, his charge
    being completed.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    2 p., 31 x 30 cm
    Regarding the fortifications of
    Berwick, destruction or restoration?
    King's departure delayed by selection
    of officers and councillors. Seeks
    leave to return for Parliament ahead
    of King.
  - All the Committee to Lord Mandeville; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 28 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Jealousies and suspicions that they
    must remain in Scotland to the benefit
    of some faction, fear of ill weather,
    desire to be at Parliament; requests
    leave to return, charges being done.
  - All the Committee to Michael Ernely; Edinburgh, 1641 Sep 29 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    L 18,000 for the garrison at Berwick
    on its way; L 18,000 (11,000?) to
    follow. Authority to slight the outer
    works of the town; if orders for
    Committee are sent to Berwick, send
    them on.
  - All the Committee to Court of the Bishoprick of Durham; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Invitation by Lord General and
    Officers of Scots Army to perform
    some act of justice between
    Soldiers and Landlords where they
    billeted. Relations between them
    mentioned.
  - All the Committee to Michael Ernely; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Enclosure wanting.
    Returning arms of Townsmen seized
    needs warrant to keep the arms and
    munitions at Berwick.
  - All the Committee to Michael Ernely; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    1 p., 30 x 20 cm
    Declining to oversee the matters
    at Berwick, leaving them instead
    to Michael Ernely.
  - All the Committee to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Gratitude for letters and intimation
    that orders for their return are
    being sent.
  - Fiennes, Armyne, Stapelton, and Hampden to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Evidently has been made Lt. Gov.
    of Berwick; recommends title not
    be taken away; will not have
    been to Berwick.
  - Lord Howard to Lord Keeper Littleton; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    2 p., 29 x 20 cm
    News of plot to seize Marquess
    Hamilton, Earl of Argyle and Earl
    of Lanericke, also of depositions
    in Parliament by a Captain Stewart.
  - All the Committee to Michael Ernely; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    1 p., 29 x 19 cm
    Acknowledges information of King's
    command to disbanding the remainder
    of the garrison; will send more on
    question of removing the drawbridge
    and gates.
  - All the Committee to Pym; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    The garrison is now disbanded; the
    Scots have withdrawn to the city.
    Due to differences over examination
    of Marquess Hamilton and Earl of
    Argyle nothing has been done.
  - All the Committee to William Carnaby; Edinburgh, 1641 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    As Ernely has already begun slighting
    the works at Berwick, does not plan
    to visit; question of drawbridge,
    inner works. Works near Sir James
    Douglas' to be slighted as well.
- Documents, 1640 Dec 16; Series II
  - DS; Adam Blair; no place, 1640 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    7 p., 31 x 20 cm
    Scottish committee charges against
    E. of Strafford.
  - DS; Adam Blair; no place, 1640[1] Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Schedule containing particular
    sums of Scottish losses and charges.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Acquittals of John, Earl of Traquair
    and James, E. of Montrose.
  - Document; no place, [1641 Aug] (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Appt. of Committee -- E. of Bedford,
    Lord Howard, Armine, Stapelton,
    et. al. and their duties.
  - Document; no place, [1641 Aug] (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Petition to Charles I to accept
    Lord Howard et. al. as Commissioners
    to act as intermediates between King
    and Parliament.
  - DS; William Lenthall and Edward Littleton; no place, 1641 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    2 p., 29 x 19 cm
    Ordinance of Parliament with
    instructions to the Committee.
  - DS; E. of Holland to Viscount Grandison; no place, 1641 Sep (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Instructions...to be observed by him
    in his present journey into Scotland.
  - DS; John Browne; no place, 1641 Sep 8 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    4 p., 30 x 19 cm
    Instructions to the Committee of
    both Houses now in Edinburgh.
  - DS; John Browne and Henry Elsynge; no place, 1641 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    5 p., 30 x 19 cm
    Instructions to be sent to the
    Committee of both houses now
    attending his majesty at Edinburgh.
  - DS; John Browne; no place, 1641 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    2 p., 30 x 19 cm
    Concerning the raising and
    transporting forces of horses
    and soldiers.
  - DS; John Browne and Henry Elsynge, 1641 Sep 9 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Concerning raising and transporting
    forces of horses and foot out of his
    Majesty's kingdom.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 45)
    King to nominate officers and
    councillors subject to Scottish
    Parliament's opposition.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Also concerning King's nomination of
    Scots officers and councillors.
    Suggests recess for the Commission
    of the Council.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Answers to doubts proposed by King
    on election of officers, etc.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Unlabelled orders 1-7: Commission
    for ordering Treasury be drawn up,
    Agenda of Scottish Parliament(?).
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    1 p., 18 x 20 cm
    King's message to Parliament,
    refusal to grant commission,
    disbanding of Army.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    1 p., 15 x 20 cm fragment
    Will welcome any members of English
    Parliament to be present at Scottish
    Parliament's ratification of the
    treaty.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Summaries of King's request of
    Committee (?) to write to Berwick,
    to not write to Parliament, to write
    Lord Keeper regarding week by week
    adjournment.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Committee's response to King's
    request: to wait for word from
    Parliament on slowly disbanding
    garrison, to report to Parliament,
    to let Parliament decide
    adjournments.
  - DS; Jo[hn] Throckmorton DCP; no place, 1641 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    1 p., 30 x 19 cm
    Commanding Lord Howard's return, as
    requested in his last letter.
  - DS; Jo[hn] Throckmorton DCP; no place, 1641 Oct 5 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    1 p., 22 x 19 cm
    Note to Committee -- high burgesses,
    several burgesses and assistants.
  - DS; Jo[hn] Throckmorton DCP; no place, 1641 Oct 5 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Provisions for public safety due to
    disbanding of the army.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Captain William Stewart's
    deposition on the E. of Crawford's
    plot against Marquesses Hamilton
    and Argyle.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Opposition to public trial of a
    recent incident.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    2 p., 29 x 18 cm
    A Sillogism for the Private
    Committee: advocates private Committee
    for examination of secret plots before
    examination in Parliament.
  - Document; no place, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 59)
    3 p., 29 x 19 cm
    Declaration of Parliament against
    this new plot.
  - Document; no place, 1641 Oct (Box 1, Folder 60)
    3 p., 30 x 19 cm
    Instructions from Parliament to the
    Committee of both Houses attending
    Charles I: on E. of Crawford's
    plot, treaty with Scotland, disbanding
    of garrisons at Carlisle and Berwick.
- Letters Catalogued Separately, Series III
  - BARRINGTON, SIR THOMAS, BART., C. 1589-1644
    - ALS to Lord Howard; Hatfield Broadoaks, Essex, 1641 Jul 24 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      3 p., 32 x 21 cm, with address
      Mentions difficulties in executing
      ordinances for disarming papists and
      collecting Poll-money. Assures
      Ld. Howard of country's support
      of Parliament.
  - LITTLETON, EDWARD LITTLETON, 1ST BARON, 1589-1645
    - 2 ALS (one signed) to [Lord Howard], 1641, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 62)
      2 p., 29 x 18 cm, 20 x 14 cm
      Regarding letters to and replies from
      committee appointed by House of Peers.